Hi everyone, thanks for joining the
DProgram show with Ted R and John
Kuryaku. Uh it is a pleasure to be
joined today by reality winner. reality
winner is of course uh I would say an
American hero. Uh she's the author of a
new book called I Am Not Your Enemy. Um
great read. Uh go out and get it. Uh
she's also a former US uh Air Force uh
senior airman as well as a former uh and
also an NSA whistleblower who served
time in federal prison for violating the
Espionage Act. something that you and
John have in common. Um, so, uh, let's
just get to it. Um, and talk about, uh,
you know, I'm I think, you know, I'm not
going to go chronologically here. I'm
going to I think it's start important to
say, so let's get to the main event. we
can work backwards to the chronological
stuff, but I I'm super I wrote a book
about Edward Snowden and um you know,
one of the and my weighin for for that
book and I'm really interested in I I'm
so honored to be with really both of you
here today um was the fact that you know
hundreds of thousands of people had
access to the same exact information as
Edward Snowden and only he chose to step
forward and I wanted to kind of know
what was it about him, why him? Why not
all these other people that caused him
to see all these things that were
plainly wrong, illegal, um violating the
Constitution and our basic privacy
rights of Americans and people around
the world. Um why did he what was
different about him? And so, you know,
that that was the exploration that I was
interested in and I think I'm interested
in that with you as well. So, um,
reality, if you can just sort of tell
us, um, where you were working, uh, when
the NSA document in question
came into, you know, crossed your
crossed your path and, uh, sort of what
happened next.
Well, I will say I have so much in
common with Ed Snowden, and I'll get to
that at the end of this answer. But to
start off, I was working at Fort Gordon,
Georgia. Um, it was what I considered a
temporary position to uh renew my
security clearance, which was going to
expire um the January after I had gotten
out of the Air Force. So they expire
like every five years I think or
something like that. I think I had
started it in 20
um
whatever it was it was going to expire
very soon and because I didn't have an
active position at NSA. The job
recruiters that I was talking to trying
to get a position at Bram in Afghanistan
weren't interested in hiring me until I
had an active security clearance. And so
I just took the next available position
as a linguist. I didn't even know if it
was going to be on Fort me or Fort
Gordon. I just took it um and hoped for
the best.
>> Fort me is NSA headquarters.
>> Yep. In Maryland. Yeah.
>> Um I had rented a house in Georgia and
so I had accepted a job and luckily that
job happened to be in Georgia as well or
else I would have panicked. Um, but they
renewed my security clearance during
that year and I was already at the time
of my arrest um, talking to other
recruiters trying to get a new contract
in Afghanistan.
>> And you were a translator in two of the
well in three of the major languages
spoken in Afghanistan, right? Pashto,
Dari, which is Persian and Arabic.
>> Not Arabic yet. It's always been
something I've been trying to learn on
and off again.
Um, but like it's kind of like one of
those things where if you read like a
sign in Spanish and you're like, "Oh, I
kind of like given the context, I know
what they're saying. If I had like, you
know, something in Arabic at like a
restaurant or something, I I could
figure it out."
>> Okay.
>> Yeah. So, one of the things that led me
to be kind of vulnerable is that I was
very disconnected from what I was doing
because they gave me Farsy, which was an
Iranian mission. which I was not
interested in. And then also they had
assigned me to this workshop and nobody
really knew I was there. It was just one
of those wonderful uses of our tax
dollars where they were just giving
people contracts and then putting them
in offices and nobody knew what I was
actually sent there to do. And my direct
supervisor was overwhelmed and he was
one of those guys that doesn't know how
to delegate. M.
>> So he was like, you know, just go do
this, go do busy work because I don't
have the emotional capacity right now to
bring you on board to this mission. So
that was my first three months of
working at that contract when I saw the
document. Um,
>> so you're at you're at a p So this is
not the you're not at NSA, you're at a
private contracting company. Yeah. No, I
am in NSA government contractors. I am
in Fort Gordon in the giant shiny NSA
building that was brand new at the time.
>> Gotcha. Go ahead. Yeah. Um, but what I
will say is when I read I read Edward
Snowden's um, autobiography
or his memoir in prison, someone sent it
to me and I think what you touched on
like why one individual saw it is that
when he went over his childhood, we had
played all the same video games, you
know, being very similar in age. And the
point of all of these video games,
Kingdom Hearts, Legend of Zelda, um I
think he listed a couple more, but he
was really into Zelda. And it's just
you're one person.
>> He also liked Magic the Gathering,
right?
>> Yeah. And it's like it's very much one
person in that universe. like we call it
now like main character energy. But a
lot of us millennials that grew up with
these storylines, it's one person who
wakes up and realizes they're special
and they can do something that nobody
else can. And I think we both kind of
had that sort of like
this is going to be really hard. There's
going to be some really evil people, but
it's going to be an adventure.
>> I have a question for you. reality. One
of the things that I learned very early
on in my own whistleblowing experience
is that almost no whistleblowers
consider themselves to be
whistleblowers. In fact, when I when I
met with Jesseline Raak from the
Government Accountability Project for
the very first time, it was just a
couple of days after my arrest. Um
I was walking out of her office and I
said, "Thank you so much for for helping
me. I know that you help whistleblowers
and I'm not a whistleblower. And she
said, "You are a whistleblower." I said,
"I'm not. I'm just a guy."
And she said, I I remember her exact
words. She said, "There's a legal
definition of whistleblowing. It is
bringing to light any evidence of waste,
fraud, abuse, illegality, or threats to
the public health or public safety." She
said, "Motivation is irrelevant." Mhm.
>> Well, it was my experience after that
that Ed didn't think he was a
whistleblower. Uh, looking back at Tom
Drake, Tom was adamant that he wasn't
the whistleblower. And of course, in the
end, we all were. We just didn't realize
it. I remember in early comments that
you made that you said you weren't the
whistleblower. And it made me chuckle
because we had all go gone through the
same thing. Do you see now how important
your whistleblowing was? Has it finally
registered with you now that you you
have the the benefit of a of a few years
uh where you can look back and and see
how you how you affected the the
political debate on these issues?
>> I don't simply because
>> I knew you were going to say that.
>> I think that part of like the the
definition of whistleblower does not
include sneaking documents out in your
underwear. Um
>> or how about on a thumb drive if you're
Edward Snowden?
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah, exactly. Um,
so for me, just because I know that
even though it did affect public safety
in a way, it wasn't necessarily
something that the
um it was not something that showed that
our government was doing something wrong
or malicious to the American people. And
I did do the illegal thing of sending it
to a journalist. And you know, I wish I
And that was one of the things too of
feeling so isolated was seeing that and
just being so certain that every other
individual that works for the federal
government had also seen it.
>> And that wasn't true. Like I should have
taken that document straight to
Congress. If I had driven that up and
handed it to a senator that I had
trusted,
>> then I would say I'm a whistleblower,
but instead I sent it to an online news
agency. And
it was
outside of my power, it was completely
ineffective
because they had no interest in giving
that document to the public.
>> Right.
>> Only until they found out that I had
been arrested.
>> Right. So, let's so let's continue with
like the um and
I mean Tom Drake and Ed Snowden both Tom
Drake did go the cong the congressional
route and was frustrated uh and it
didn't work to say the least.
>> Didn't work in that he it bought him
seven counts of espionage and two counts
of theft of government property which
was the information that he walked out
with in his head. Snowden took note of
that and that's why he went the uh the
uh the the the media route. So, okay.
So, you're you're So, okay, go on.
You're you're back at NSA and I mean I'm
interested in the in the document and
like you know what it was and you know
why you thought it was important and
needed to come to public attention.
Honestly, it was just like the most read
report at the time. And everybody was
like maybe not the document itself, but
um this information is going to be
leaked either by Congress or it's going
to be like it's going to be in the news
by this weekend. And it wasn't.
>> So if you thought it was going to be
leaked, why did you leak it?
>> Because it wasn't.
So tell us what was in it for people who
don't know.
>> I can't say.
>> Okay. All right. So I can say um so uh
according to news reports um this was a
document that uh that that basically
it's a report about uh Russian attempts
to hack into um election um into
election counting mechanisms during the
2016 election and using uh fish spearing
attacks which is basically uh sending an
email for example or a text and saying
like please click here um in order to
try to gain access to uh information and
uh voter registration, voter info, etc.
Uh and so basically this was evidence,
possible evidence of Russian, let's just
say maybe not interference in an
election, but certainly an attempt to
gain access to private information that
should not be available to anyone but
the board of elections, I think is fair
to say. Okay. So, you see the document
in question
and um you and you thought it needed to
come to the attention the public needed
to know. Yeah.
>> Yeah.
>> Why?
Because in 2017 that was there was one
question
that was being asked every single day
and it was not something that we had as
a nation really
um had faced before like people it was
just one debate that was going on and I
honestly felt like it was the NSA's
job or at least it was someone in
government's job to
lay bare the actual facts for everybody.
I get just felt like that was their
responsibility instead of letting it
fment to such a toxic level that
you know
things weren't getting done you know but
obviously that government administration
wasn't going to do it.
>> Um and it just frustrated me so much.
Um
your mom and stepfather were very very
active around your um your trial and
your incarceration. Uh they did
literally everything they could think of
to uh to draw friendly uh support to
your cause. And at the end of the first
Trump administration, they were actively
seeking a pardon or a commutation for
you. Did you make any headway in that
first time around and would you consider
applying for a pardon the second time
around?
>> Um, so right now the office of the
pardon is not available and I think just
based off of like a general moral
decency this time around. I'm not really
interested in having things in common
with like
January 6 insurrectionists,
>> right? Um, at the time at the end of the
first Trump presidency,
uh, we were absolutely languishing in
federal prison due to the COVID
pandemic.
>> And my whole story, it's kind of like a
slapstick comedy because it's like, you
know, one scene it's uh, Comey and Trump
in, you know, in the Oval Office and and
in their respective government agencies
saying the next person that leaks is
going to die. And then you have me
mailing the document out because like
doo I had no idea that was being said.
>> Yeah.
>> Um we had somebody in our team get a
memo about my pardon
in the White House on its way to the
Oval Office. Like it was right there
outside of the door
and the news broke about the call with
Zalinski getting leaked.
So obviously no sympathy for leaker.
Like the person with the memo just
turned around and walked away.
>> Timing is a [__]
>> It is. I can tell you in my own case
too. Um and I I got this from someone
with direct like regular access to the
president. He told me that on the last
day of the Trump presidency, January
19th of 2017,
that he was preparing to pardon Julian
Assange, Ed Snowden, and me, and got a
call from Mitch McConnell. Um, now Mitch
McConnell has never heard of me, but
Mitch McConnell told Donald Trump, "If
you pardon Assange and Snowden,
I will release Republican senators to
vote their conscience on whether or not
to convict you on the charges that had
been referred to the House." And so
Trump canled the pardons.
There was that kind of pressure from
Republican senators and he he caved.
He did pardon Lil Wayne though.
>> You know what? And that was the nature
of the call that I got from my friend.
He says, "Are you sitting down?" And I
said, "Yeah, what's going on?" And he
said, "He's pardoning little Wayne." And
I said, "Little Wayne." And he says,
"Little [__] Wayne is getting a
pardon today." I was like, "Oh my god."
I said, "The world's upside down. I
don't know what I'm going to do."
>> It's very [__] up. Um, okay. So, I I
want to get back to the leak, though.
So, uh, you you you get this document,
you you print it out at work.
Correct me if I if I'm wrong about any
of these details. You you you you and
you sent it off to The Intercept, which
is, of course, uh, the progressive uh,
formed by uh, founded by Pier Odiar, uh,
media organization that was, uh, where
Glenn Greenwald was working at the time
as a as an editor. Um, and you were
obviously hoping that they would publish
some an article about it and uh bring it
to the attention of the American people.
Um, in terms of spy craft or trade
craft, um, did you I mean did what steps
were you concerned about being caught
and uh, so what what steps did you take?
Like for example, did you avoid putting
fingerprints on the package? Did you
mail it from far away? Did you know I
know you got caught because of the
printer but and also because the
intercept [__] up but uh they were
really incredibly um careless to say the
least. Shoddy journalism to say the
least. Um
>> but anyway so what steps did you take?
Did you handr write did you handw write
the label? Did you print out the label?
You know what I mean?
>> Um so it was just um how to get the
document out the building. Um, so don't
carry it out.
Um, uh, like I said, I I did hand write
the label. I did put to the intercept on
it, right? Um, I just put like a generic
name and then sent it to their secure
mailing address. I did not mail it right
away. I just sent it from a USPS box
that was most convenient for me, like a
day later. uh the one that was nearest
to the yoga studio where I just happened
to be subbing that night.
Um
other than that, I just knew that the
envelope being nondescript and getting
to the intercept.
Um they would see it, realize it was
important, I guess, verify it. I don't
know. It had the logo. Like what more
was there to verify?
um and that information would be
released to the people and
>> and you thought this was going to a
journalistic organization so you didn't
have to worry about you know the FBI
crawling all over uh you know searching
for fingerprints and uh you know you're
basically sending it to Bob Woodward in
1972. Right.
>> Right.
>> Exactly. And I had thought too is like
everything was so high-tech. They're
looking for thumb drives. They're not
going to be like, "Oh, they got this
information
from a piece of paper sent in the mail."
Like, they were going to be looking for
or if they had not just like thrown the
document out there in the public,
they would be like, "Okay, well, who in
Congress is calling the press?" You
know, like they would have thought it
would be given like orally over the
phone or by WhatsApp or something
secure, not like the lowest possible
technical means.
>> This is like when they mailed the pope
the hope diamond. Um,
>> exactly.
>> What did Why did you choose the
intercept?
>> Because
>> they sent it to me. I wouldn't have
turned that wouldn't have happened to
you if you'd sent it to me.
>> Um, because they said if you see
something, leak something. Um, they did
have their history with Snowden. They
were all former government veterans.
>> They really cared about national
security.
>> Um, I mean, they were talking about
Yemen in 2015. Nobody was talking about
Yemen in 2015. These guys were so
connected and queued in and talking
about the things that mattered because I
felt like they were like me. They were
seeing the bigger picture. And I
thought, of course, these people are
going to know exactly
how to give this information out to have
the best effect possible.
>> Did you consider Wikileaks?
>> Um, I didn't really know how to use the
dark web, so no, that wasn't really an
option. I'm not good with computers. I'm
good at breaking computers.
>> Okay, so the intercept, so the intercept
receives it. um from what we know um
they they get the package
and they first of all we don't know that
they're interested in even doing an
article they don't seem to find it
interesting and we I want to get to that
but someone from the intercept the rep
reporter who's assigned to it or who's
dealing with it then takes it to his
buddy at the NSA and basically says hey
will you verify this and hands not like
a photo of it or image of it, but like
the actual physical envelope and paper.
I mean, I'm sorry. He went full [__]
Yeah.
>> And and he handed it over to the NSA,
who of course
>> went to work doing what the NSA does
>> and in probably five seconds, right,
they had like the everything that people
don't know. I didn't know this until I
read about your case that like
everything that's printed out of from a
from a printer like I have one right
behind me here has a little uh invisible
dot kind of like an old fax machine like
identifying piece uh image but you can't
it's a it's a watermark and uh you can
ex you can get to it if you know what to
do. NSA knew what to do. So they were
able to be like, "Oh, this this machine
is at this office at at NSA."
And so at that point, your arrest is
becomes inevitable.
>> Is that basically right?
>> It is. Um he didn't give them the
envelope at first. This is how freaking
stupid it was. His friend was like,
"Wow, that's really interesting. Can I
see the envelope where it came from?"
And then he's like, "Sure. I mean, it's
just an Augusta, Georgia area code
stamped on the envelope. What What harm
could come from that?
>> I'll tell you,
>> you should never work in journalism
again. Sorry.
>> Well, you know what? Let me let me add
to that. Uh because that's an important
statement you just made, Ted. The the
two the two Intercept journalists that
were responsible for sending you to
prison were the two Intercept
journalists responsible for sending me
to prison.
>> No way. And oh, the same guys. The two
same guys.
>> And Daniel Hail and Terry Aubry.
>> Thank you for saying that. You're
exactly right. I tweeted after your
arrest. I tweeted
serious I tweeted at the Intercept. I
said serious question at Intercept.
Are you guys just [__] stupid or are
you working for the FBI?
>> It's a good [__] question.
And of course they never responded but
it was a serious question. If you are a
national security journalist then you
know and have known since you became a
national security journalist that
identifying information is embedded in
the in the documents. It can be in the
dot of an eye. It can be in a period.
The the naked eye can't see it. That's
why they wanted an actual copy of the
document.
>> Of course
>> that they could see where it came from.
But if you're a national security
journalist, one who who you know has a
website about himself and about what a
great and important national security
journalist he is that he's either a
[__] or he's working for the
government. One
>> John any any journalist. You don't have
to be a national security journalist.
Any journalist. I mean you don't burn a
source. I mean you know you go to you go
to prison for the rest of your life
rather than burn.
>> Look at poor Daniel Hail. Poor Daniel
Hail. He he gives uh his information to
the intercept and then they put him on a
three-member panel to repeat the
information that he gave them. It was it
was a matter of hours.
>> I mean, John, you bring up an important
point. I mean, if if in terms of the
intercept guys, right? I mean, like if
if they're not going to run an article
and there's no Oh, kitty. Um if there's
if if you're not going to run the piece,
you don't need to authenticate it.
>> No.
>> Right. You don't need to authenticate
the material at all.
>> No. Yeah, exactly. They they were taking
themselves way too seriously. Um
>> Matt Cole is just messy. It's by design
so that they can be like, "Oh, well, we
stand with the martyrs of free speech or
the martyrs of whistleblowing." Like,
you can't really have a whistleblower
without somebody getting caught, right?
>> And be like an anonymous whistleblower.
Nobody likes that story.
>> And
>> so he's doing it by design. I've got a
monkey on my back. Oh my gosh.
>> Dad usually does too.
>> Yeah. Yeah.
>> But um it's completely on purpose. Um
and my goal moving forward is to make
sure that everybody knows that. They
will purposefully screw you over so they
have something to write about.
>> Yeah.
>> That's all they do.
>> You're really convinced of that.
>> Fully convinced that all they do is
cause chaos. And that's why um Laura
Press isn't there anymore. there were
some people that cared and it's like
even at the point to where I know that
Glenn was the number one voice that did
not want to publish the document.
>> Why?
um certain countries that um he's
interested in, stuff like that. But he
didn't
>> You think it was political like
basically because of the narrative uh
that was contained in there like like
went counter to his personal politics?
>> Exactly. Yeah. It went counter to his
own personal interest, so he didn't want
to publish it. And I I felt some type of
way about that at first, but then I
realized like he wasn't even there. Like
he just said, "We're not going to
publish it. If they never published it,
then I don't go to prison." It was
Matthew Cole being messy like, "Oh,
we're not going to publish this,
but I want to give it to my buddy
because now I want to find out where it
came from."
>> Like, why would you verify something if
Glenn said don't publish it?
>> So, like,
>> he should he should have set it on fire.
Exactly. They should have disposed of
it. Just let it go. And that's honestly
what I did. That's I think one of the
reasons why I don't remember why I
walked out with that document because
for three weeks afterwards I was like,
"Oh, like they're not going to publish
it." Like let me just pretend like this
never happened. So wait, so for a couple
of days, were you expecting to turn on
the even to see a news a news alert on
your phone like breaking and it was
going to be like, "Oh my god, that's
me."
>> I think I was shaking for six straight
days. Like I was like giving myself
ulcers over it.
>> Yeah.
>> And then by like day 10, I was like,
"Okay, it's lost in the mail. Let's just
never do this again."
>> I threw it into a hole.
>> Yeah. I just like locked that away. I
just compartmentalized it and moved on.
>> [__] I'm so sorry. Um, God, I mean, I'm
so ashamed for my profession, really.
Um, and I have all every time I've
thought about that, I've always been
like, these [__] [__] Okay, so
all right, so what happens next?
>> Um,
well, and that's why people are like,
why did you go to Bise and come back?
Right? Because I had just like thrown
away the memory that I had done
something terrible. Um, and then
>> the timing there. So like you So you
after how long after you mailed did you
>> two weeks probably about two weeks. I
mailed the document like on a Tuesday
and then a couple
>> by the way I stayed at the same at one
of the same hotels as you did. They told
me they were there. It's pretty funny.
>> The monkey resort.
>> Yes. Amazing.
>> My favorite place in the world. Oh my
gosh.
>> Beautiful. Yeah.
>> Um wonderful family too. Yes. really
like those people. Um,
>> so yeah, it's just like then they had
showed up and obviously now we know with
the Broadway play and the the movie
um just how
violating that uh completely consensual
interview was, right? Um I was free to
walk away at any time.
>> So So wait, so let's go back to that. So
let's set the stage. Sorry, reality. So,
you're home when they show up or you
come home and they're already there.
What happens?
>> I had just come home and then that was
another thing too like one of the ways
that they kind of especially for women
that they try to put you off guard
>> is that on Saturday mornings like I get
up and I was out the door by 6:30 to the
gym.
>> Um I was at the gym for maybe four
hours. um went out to lunch with a boy
and then was supposed to go back to his
place that night to watch a movie, but I
needed
groceries and stuff like that cuz I meal
prep on Sundays. So, I went to like the
nearest Kroger and my whole thing was I
was not drinking alcohol at the time,
but I was like, I kind of want to bring
like one of the larger 22 ounce craft
beer bottles over. And so, I had picked
one up. I had put it in the dairy, gone
back and gotten it, walked around a bit,
gone and grabbed a different one, walked
around a bit, gotten a six-pack, walked
around a bit, and then went back for
another bottle and then put the bottle
like it was for me. I like obviously I
didn't know the FBI was following me.
>> So, I didn't get back to my house till
like 2:30, 3:00 in the afternoon. And so
I pull up and I park and I'm like
grabbing like my freaking giant bag of
kale and ice cream from my car and they
pull in behind me and they're like,
"Hey, you've been gone a while."
And I'm like, "Okay, I'm sorry." Like I
was just like so embarrassed because
like you realize, "Oh my gosh, they're
following me. They're probably thinking
I am an evil genius trying to lose them
on my trail and I just can't decide.
>> You knew you knew immediately when you
saw them who it was.
>> No,
>> no,
>> no. Because they had no identification.
They just looked like they were there
for Masters the golf tournament because
they were wearing like pastel polo
shirts.
>> Yeah, I've seen them.
>> And I think Garrick was wearing like
Yeah, he was wearing like sky blue and
Taylor was wearing like literally like
Pepto-Bismol pink. And they didn't they
didn't present IDs or
>> they did and then they said um we do
have a warrant. We're looking for some
documents
and that's when I was like okay well I
don't have any documents anymore.
They're going to search and I'm going to
figure this out later. Mhm.
>> Um,
>> were you hoping at that point that you
might be able that this might still all
go away, that you'd might be able to
satisfy their answers and just be like,
I don't know anything about it
>> and uh they don't they search the house,
they don't find anything. Maybe they're
like,
>> right. Um, and it's one of those things
that it's a legal technicality that I
didn't pick up on the time, but one of
the reasons why we went to court and we
argued that I was not free to walk away
is they had a warrant to search my
physical person.
>> And so until they executed the physical
body search, no, I was not free to
leave. And so the interrogation happened
between the time they searched the house
and the time they brought a female
officer because they never sent the FBI
did not send a single woman to my house.
They sent 11 men and they needed a woman
to put hands on me to search my body.
But by that time, I had already
confessed because of our completely air
quotes consensual interview.
>> Why didn't you just uh roll John Kuryaku
style and say I am represented by
council and I don't talk to cops?
>> Well, I made them the same mistake that
that reality made because up until that
point, anytime the FBI ever asked me
anything, I would say, "Hey, anything
for the FBI? Anything I can do to be
helpful? I'm a patriot, right? Just like
reality. So, it never occurred to me
when they started asking me questions
and they tricked me, of course, just
like they tricked her. Um, they said,
"Hey, remember that case you helped us
out with two years ago?" And there was
this case. I said, "Sure." They said,
"We need your help again." And I said,
"Anything for the FBI."
And then they
>> famous last words.
reality. I mean, surely it must have
occurred to you that, you know, maybe I
should shut up now.
>> No, because they looked like all the
guys in my office and I worked for the
NSA. They're the FBI
in and being a white woman from a middle
class background where my mom worked
with uniformed
police officers as a child protective
service investigator.
For me also just like with the intercept
kind of listening to them so much I
don't or I didn't view the FBI as law
enforcement. I viewed them as more of a
government agency.
And so I did was not in any way, shape,
or form thinking about like, oh, I'm
talking to cops. These are the same
uniform cops that murder Freddy Gay in
Baltimore. I wasn't. That wasn't my
thing.
>> Or the Black Panthers in Chicago,
>> you know. And that was the thing, too,
is I never had that education.
I was just in that era of learning about
um the prison industrial system,
>> you know, six month if you had given me
six months of going down that rabbit
hole and learning about things in the
country. Like I didn't even know about
like Coen Intel Pearl.
>> I didn't know any of that stuff. I
didn't know. You could have asked me who
Jay Edgar Hoover was and I would have
thought he invented a vacuum cleaner
because my whole life from the time I
was 11 years old,
all I cared about was Afghanistan, 9/11,
and the Taliban and how to learn as many
languages as possible.
>> Really? Any Do you mind if I ask you how
old you are?
>> I am 33.
>> Okay.
>> Yeah. I mean, you're so young to have
gone through all this, just like Ed. Um,
so all right. So obviously you talk to
them. I've seen the I I mean I have seen
I've seen the movie, but for those who
haven't um they talked to you for hours,
right? And then
>> like an hour like two hours and then
arrested you?
>> Yes.
>> Okay. So um at that point I mean are you
thinking I need an attorney? I mean I'm
in deep [__] What are you thinking?
>> So,
this is where like the real trauma [__]
starts to happen because and I think
John can kind of um
give you a little bit more backup
information because so remember how like
Thomas Drake was arrested for like what
was in his mind, right? It doesn't have
to be a tangible physical piece of paper
with a top secret label on it. Mhm.
>> We had been told because I had actually
worked for the NSA at the time of
Snowden's leaks, at the time of Chelsea
Manning, and we were not allowed to read
news articles about them because those
news articles, the way you introduced my
case, somebody who has a current topsec
clearance could not listen to this
podcast
if there's still classified information
being played on their device, but they
are now holding digital signatures of
top secret information.
>> Ridiculous.
>> So, I didn't know what they had gone
through and I didn't know if this was a
process that an attorney could help
with.
>> All I had known is that when they first
got Chelsea, she went and spent nine
months in solitary confinement at
Quantico.
And so, Agent Garrick and Taylor did not
say, "You are under arrest." They didn't
read the Miranda rights that you see on
Law and Order in CIS.
>> I've never had my Miranda rights read to
me. Never.
>> Did they handcuff you?
>> So, that's it was the weirdest arrest
ever. And it's either that's just they
were awkward about it or, you know,
white privilege comes into play. But
Agent Garrick said, "Yeah, we're going
to have to take you in." Is how he told
me I was under arrest. He said, "We're
going to go in this vehicle." And he
gestured to one of the black unmarked
government vehicles. He said, "I will be
sitting next to you the whole time." He
said that we will cuff your hands in the
front
so you won't be uncomfortable. The only
thing I want to apologize for is that
it's going to be a bit of a drive.
And that's when I thought, "Holy [__]
[__] we're going to Quantico."
>> And you had animals at home, right?
>> Yes. So that was when I was like, I'm
going to Quantico. I don't know how to
tell my parents that.
And that was when he gave me my cell
phone back to call somebody to come get
the dogs. So I didn't call my parents
because they're not in Georgia. Um I
called the lady at the animal rescue. Um
cuz I had she's like the last person I
had spoken to that week. Like I came
home from BISE, she dropped my dog off
and then I went to work for 3 days, went
to the gym and got arrested. Like that's
what had happened. So, I had just seen
her. She knew where the house was. I
just said, "Hey, Kathy, I need you to
come get my dog and my cat. I don't know
what's going on, but um I am in a bit of
trouble and I just need you to come get
my animals sometime tomorrow. Uh I can't
even take care of my cat right now." She
said, "Okay." And I said, "I can't I
can't talk any longer. Like, this is
it." So, she got off the phone. I got
off the phone. I handed my phone back to
Garrick
and he's like, "Why do you think you're
in trouble?"
>> I was like
I was like, "You just like bas I'm like
I'm going to Quantico. Like what do you
mean? Like you just told me
>> I have handcuffs on. It's kind of it's
kind of a tell,
>> right? Like like I had just confessed to
you. Like we all like why are you doing
this?" So anyway, then he's like, well,
don't you want to call your family? I
was like, I thought I got one phone call
and these two living creatures in my
house are important. Like, duh. Like, I
like the whole thing was like, look at
this [__] sociopathic [__] All she
cares about is her dog and her cat.
She's not going to even tell her family
is how I felt. You know what I mean?
Like,
>> once they brought that up, did you say
yes, I would like to call my parents?
Yeah. And so he's like, "Okay." And then
again, oh, so they said we're going to
have to take you in. They never said you
are charged with this law. I wasn't
arraigned yet. It wasn't even like that
yet. It was just like at no point.
Nobody said the word espionage.
So I still didn't even know exactly
uh the technicalities of what I had done
wrong. Right. Like we just had we had an
action and a result. I didn't know where
I was going. Okay. So, I called my dad
because, you know, I never tell my mom
when I'm in trouble. I always tell my
dad. And um I was just like, "Hey, like
again, I was like, I'm in trouble. I
don't know where I'm going, but the FBI
is here and
um I guess I'm going with them. Um I I
don't have any information." Like, I
didn't have any information.
>> Mhm. Like I was like, I didn't even know
these guys were cops. Like what do you
think? Like it was so crazy. And then
agent Garrick's just like just give me
the phone. Give me the phone. And he
grabs the phone and like my heart rate
is so high at that time. Like he walks
away from me and I don't hear what he's
telling my dad.
So basically he they already had me on
the schedule to be arraigned that t that
Monday or Tuesday.
>> Ah let me interrupt you. They do that on
purpose. They like to make their arrests
on Thursdays
>> because there are no arraignments on
Fridays and so you have to spend
Thursday night, Friday night, Saturday
night, and Sunday night in in the local
jail, which in DC is a very dangerous
place and then they reign you on Monday
after you've been beaten up a couple of
times and softened up and are much more
willing than you were on Thursday to
take a plea.
>> Yeah. So, you know, luckily I was
arrested on a Saturday afternoon,
>> right?
>> Um, but yeah, so he was the one that How
the [__] would I have that information?
Like, hey, meet me at the federal
courthouse in Augusta, Georgia at 9:00
a.m. on Monday. You know what I mean?
Like, that's what he told my dad
apparently. I never heard that
conversation. And then he takes my phone
and then we had that very dangerous
conversation about how to turn my phone
on because I didn't know how. And I was
like, "Well, you press the button on the
side and you like you swipe up." And
they were like, "Whoa, whoa, whoa. Don't
do that." And I was like, "But that's
how you unlock it." And they were like,
"Well, what's the passcode?" And I'm
like, "I don't lock my phone." Like
online and mobile banking was like just
invented.
>> Uhhuh.
>> Like even if it was, like I wouldn't
have a lock on my phone. I never had a
lock on my phone. Um, so they were just
like, "Wow, why would you have a lock in
your phone?" I was like, "Can you'all
just stop [__] with me." So then that
was when these stupid idiots realized
that they had to search me um before in
order to, you know, satisfy the warrant
and none of them could touch me. So they
called somebody from the Richmond County
Sheriff's Office. A woman showed up. She
went and patted me down. There wasn't
much. I was not wearing much that day.
And then she comes back out and then
pulls Garrick and Taylor aside and she's
talking to them and I don't know what
happened. Maybe that I mean she could
have hated me for all I know. But after
that conversation all plans changed and
another sheriff's vehicle came and
another woman came out and then that's
when um Garrick said, "Hey, you're going
to go with her."
>> And you're in Richmond, Virginia at this
point.
Um I'm still in Augusta, Georgia, but
we're in Richmond County.
>> Gotcha. Okay. Right.
>> Yeah. So that's the county that I was
technically in.
>> Okay.
>> And so she came up to me and she's like,
"Hey, like I guess I'm arresting you. Um
why don't you come with me to the
vehicle?" We walk to the vehicle. She
opens the door and she's like, "Sorry,
it's policy. I've got to have you in
cuffs." So then she cuffs me behind my
back and then I get into the vehicle and
then she closed the door and then that
was the first time like as she drove
away from those FBI agents
that was the first time I realized that
I had just survived my own arrest.
Yeah. So I guess this brings up the
point the always important point that
when you're dealing with the cops u to
ask them am I under arrest? Am I free to
go? Am I being detained? Uh, and just
keep insisting on that. Okay. So, they
took you to the lockup.
>> Yeah, they took me to um the Lincoln
County Jail. So, it wasn't the one
directly by the courthouse. Um, I guess
that county jail did have a federal
contract. It was very small. It was very
secluded. And I think that's kind of why
they chose it.
Um they booked me in and then they took
me back to uh the woman's cell block was
one cell
and it used to be the disciplinary one
for the men. So it was smaller, not
quite as nice. They only had one place
for the women to be. So if the women
didn't get along, it was just playing
like rotating chairs with the one
isolation cell
>> which was literally across the hall from
us. So, like when women didn't get
along, they were still arguing across
the hallway.
Um, or if somebody did get put over
there for a fight and everybody was
supporting the person that got pulled
out,
like we would just sit at the door and
talk to them all day anyway. Like,
nobody was ever truly like in isolation
or completely alone.
So you are I mean you know I'm like okay
so where does an attorney enter the
picture?
>> My attorney showed up five minutes late
to my arraignment. Um, I was downstairs
in the holding cell and then they put me
in a very small like the room where you
get to talk to your attorney through
like the great for the first time
and
>> court ordered attorney
>> courtappointed attorney Titus. He said,
"Hey, they told me 30 minutes ago that
I'm on this case. I don't know what
you're being charged with. I'm so
sorry." He's like, "We are going to
plead guilty and we're gonna I mean, I'm
sorry. I'm so sorry." He's like, "We're
going to plead not guilty."
>> Okay.
>> Not guilty and then we'll have a
conversation about this.
>> He's like, "I have no idea what's going
on. They just told me."
>> Um, and then I said, "I don't care.
Like, how do I get out on bond?"
>> Like, everybody gets out. Like, you know
what I mean? Like, when do I get out?
>> I got out on my own recgnizance. So did
Jeffrey Sterling.
>> Yes. But I'm a terrorist. Come on.
>> Apparently,
>> obviously.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Just look at
>> dangerous to society needs to be
protected from you.
>> Pull that. They're going to pull that
out of context. It's going to be saying,
"I'm a terrorist. I'm a terrorist over
and over again." Um,
>> don't be afraid of sarcasm. It's a
humorous best friend. Anyway,
>> yeah. So,
and he was certain of that, too. He was
like, "Okay, well, they will decide when
we get there." He's like, "I'm not going
to make this girl any promises,
obviously. Um he's like, "But we will
talk about that in the courtroom." He's
like, "But just today you're going to
say your name and you're not going to
say anything else. That's how we're
going to do today until I figure out
what's going on." Um obviously that
hearing didn't go well. They said, "Oh,
well, we're not going to have a bond
hearing until Thursday."
Um I didn't obviously I couldn't talk to
my family. Um, and then that was when
Titus saw like what they were charging
me with.
And
um, I pled not guilty.
And then
was it No, it was at the hearing on
Thursday that they took away my
courtappointed attorneys because they
figured I could afford my own attorneys.
Can I jump ahead just a little bit?
>> Um,
your mom posted something on Facebook
um, just before your book came out,
reality, and she said that
your conviction precluded you from
making money from the book.
>> I found that to be outrageous.
I've made a living from my conviction.
Uh, I've written what, eight books and
at least three of them have something to
do with my conviction. Why was that
restriction placed on you? It seems it
seems like a violation of your
constitutional rights. Patently unfair.
Um, it hasn't been placed on the rest of
us. Why you?
>> I'm gonna I'm
>> gonna say something that is just so
funny, but it's because I'm a star
obviously.
>> Yeah.
>> Yes. And that's it.
>> Or you're like son of Sam. There's the
son of Sam law, right? That
>> that is
I was going to get to that. um because
they realized very early on in the case
that instead of the document and
national security, this case quickly
became about who I am as a person.
>> Y
>> and that I was actually getting a lot
more public support than they wanted.
>> Yes. Um, their last ditch effort to
embarrass me was to publish almost in
full in the court record that
conversation with the FBI.
>> Within two months, it was turned into a
Broadway play.
>> Yes.
>> Um, and so they're like, we tried to
embarrass her and now it's on Broadway
or off Broadway.
>> Um,
>> that's jiu-jitsu.
>> Exactly. like they were every time they
tried to humiliate me, we turned around
and were like, "Actually, that's why I'm
likable." Um, and so by the time of the
conviction,
they had added in there that no part
from the moment I joined the Air Force
really all the way through my time at
the NSA through the conviction and even
postconviction in prison.
nothing associated with my clearance or
my charge for me, for my associates, my
acquaintances, for my current and they
put in there current and future family
members.
Like it's like they knew my sister was
pregnant with the child at that time and
they were like that niece
will not get anything. Like it was so
petty
and because they knew that these movies
were coming out. They knew that people
were more interested in who I was as a
person
>> than the felony, the conduct that
resulted in a felony.
>> Let's talk about that reality. I mean,
I'm sorry to interrupt, but I'm I never
understood that the following aspect.
John, I totally understand why they [__]
canned him. He exposed the fact that the
US government was torturing people. In
your case, you
exposed the accusation, the allegation
that Russia was spying on our elections.
>> Um, why who why does anyone in the US
government want to defend Russia or care
what Russia is or is not doing? I mean,
you didn't embarrass them, so why are
they so upset?
>> They have this really cool dance thing.
Um, but but I did want to follow up on
that. They also knew that the only other
people who are prohibited from making
money off of their conviction are serial
killers,
>> right?
>> So, it was kind of like we double dog
dare you to use legal precedents
involving serial killers
>> to justify making money off your story,
right? Uh, so that was kind of like that
was a further slap in the face like you
know we dare you to use the same law
that men who have murdered and raped
women and are now popular in prison
um to justify making money which is why
we have never even considered appealing
it. Like that would be so repulsive to
me. Um,
so I mean for me I'm just like my last
laugh on that is I'm not making any
money but I'm not seeing a single movie
where Garrick and the lead prosecutor
Jenna or even the judge I'm not seeing a
single movie that makes them look like
good people.
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. You don't have to
>> aren't stupid.
>> I Let me ask you a followup about that
too. I um I've had a strange thing
happen to me now that my case is, you
know, more than a decade in the past. Um
three of the FBI agents that were
involved in my arrest have reached out
to me, one recently uh to apologize
and two of them called my attorneys to
apologize. one reached out to me
directly, got my email address somehow,
and said that he was sorry that he
arrested me, that he's lost sleep over
it over the last uh the last 13 years.
And that he wanted me to know that
um the orders to go after me came from
the very top and that at the working
level, they were simply following
orders. Mhm.
>> I always believed that that was the case
and it was nice to hear the apology. It
doesn't change anything, of course,
but your case seems to be so much more
clearcut than mine. Out of all the
whistleblowers, and forgive me, but I
consider you a major whistleblower. Out
of all the whistleblowers,
you're the one that violated the law the
least
in terms of the amount of of information
that was that was revealed.
It seems to me that these FBI agents,
whether they were friendly or not,
should have run to their computers to
apologize to you. Has that happened?
Have you heard from any of these people
that were involved in your case?
>> No. Well, one, I I'll talk about that at
the very end. Um,
they have not. Um,
what I do know is that I have the
satisfaction of knowing that un
everybody wanted my case cuz it was like
the first really scandalous like leak or
whatever that they could prosecute under
Trump.
>> Yes.
>> Everybody wanted this to be their career
stepping stone. And then obviously the
day I was convicted, Trump was like,
"This is stupid. This is small potatoes.
Like this is not a victory. Mhm.
>> And in hindsight, what I was hearing
once I had gotten out of prison and I
was actually listening to Joe Rogan, he
had some guy talking about it, his like
CIA guy, but he basically said
>> Mike Baker.
>> Yeah, I think it was Mike Baker.
>> He said during the Trump administration,
there were little to no FBI and CIA
promotions.
like he like basically like kneecapped
both of those agencies in that first
term. And so I was like, "Okay, well
good. Nobody got a promotion because of
me." I know that the lead prosecutor,
the mastermind behind my case, Julia
Adelstein, was fired earlier this year
because of her connections with the
Marago case. And I know that Jenna's
making a lot of money doing corporate
law, but she's not like the hot shot
national security prosecutor anymore.
So, it seems like none of them are doing
anything relevant anymore, you know?
>> I found that to be the case in
situations. Well, yeah.
>> Yeah. Like, y'all aren't doing anything
and I've got a memoir.
>> Have you gotten any apologies from The
Intercept or from Glenn Greenwald?
>> Good question.
I don't think Glenn likes me or takes me
seriously. U
>> doesn't like anybody.
>> I the apology did come from the um the
contribution to my legal team. Like
finding the legal team, finding a group
of Republicans that would defend me in
court was very important.
Um paying millions of dollars for it. Um
Jim Ryson um personally came to see me
at one point.
Um and I do know that because of her
convictions, Laura Press resigned
because she was the only one willing to
say that I got screwed over.
>> Did you ever consider suing the
Intercept?
No, because I've always
I have always just taken accountability
for the fact that regardless of what
they did, I broke the law. And I can't
be like in court saying like, "You
didn't help me break the law more
effectively."
You know, that would be like, you know,
suing your partner in a bank robbery
because they didn't grab enough cash on
the way out.
respect reality.
>> I don't know. Personally, I I would I
want to sue on your behalf.
>> I know, right?
>> Wow. Okay. So, now let's get to if I
can, if I may. Um, you know, I do want
to know the, you know, sort of why do
you think why you, you know, um why do
you think you were the person who said,
"Okay, no one else is going to release
this. Uh, I I want the country to know
and have this discussion
and I'm not just gonna wait for someone
else to do it. I'm just going to do I
I'm dropping this sucker in the mail.
>> I don't know if it's really
because of like personal aspirations or
hero complex. I think it and I don't
play like
being in a dark place like I don't blame
that
>> but I didn't have a family. Um I had
this vague dream of going to Afghanistan
and building a resume so I could work
for a humanitarian aid organization down
the line. But nothing in my future
um was really like materializing. I did
not feel like I had a bright future
ahead. In my current life, I had a
foster dog that hated everybody and a
cat. Um, like I had just lost my father.
I
couldn't stand being home.
And so like I really didn't have
anything to hold on to. So when it was
like, "Oh, you sacrificed everything."
It was like I sacrificed
the possibility of a career doing what I
dreamed of doing, but even that wasn't
tangible at the time.
>> You know,
>> so you did you feel like you didn't have
much to lose?
>> Exactly. I I didn't have anything to
lose.
>> And I thought that
I kind of thought if the information got
out first and everybody was like, "Oh my
gosh, this is so important. Whoever gave
this to us really did something great
for the country. When they did catch me,
it would, this is so dumb, but like my
favorite movie growing up was Mulan, the
cartoon one. And so at the very end,
she's standing in front of the emperor.
This is like such an Ed Snowden moment.
Like I hope he hears this because he
always talks about like Zelda and movies
and stuff like that, but the emperor
standing in front of her and he's like,
"You disgraced your family. you
illegally entered the army. You
um you foiled this plan. You blew up the
emperor's palace. You know, you did
this, you did this, you did this. And
he's like, "And you have saved us all."
And that's what I want. I wanted my
little Mulan moment.
>> What would you do different? Would you
do anything differently now? I have to
assume so. If you had to if I could pop
you, knowing what you know now, I pop
you right back in front of that post
office, that mailbox.
>> Um, are you doing any are what would you
change?
>> Yeah. So,
I'm not printing that document out. I'm
quitting my job and going to Afghanistan
and doing like a a Dan Terry moment. Um,
if I'm going to lose everything, I'm
going to lose it the way he lost it. or
I'm taking that document, driving to
Washington DC, and putting it in Bernie
Sanders hands.
>> Like, there's only two options. Don't do
it or go to prison for giving a document
to Bernie Sanders.
>> What would you say to anyone who's
thinking about leaking to the Intercept?
>> Absolutely do not leak to the Intercept.
Um
there are more effective uh journalists.
I don't know like the Washington Post is
[__] now.
>> It is um a right-wing rag. True.
>> New York Times is garbage because
>> Ed Snowden called New York Times and
left messages and they never called him
back.
>> Exactly. It's going to have to be
something done like independently. like
you are going to have to find a way to
get that information out there
independently
and do it from a safe place or accept
that your life is about to get very
hard. And that's kind of like one of the
things where it's like I'm not telling
anybody to break the law, but I'm also
telling people like me, like white
people, you're not going to El Salvador.
You're not getting sent to Sudan like at
this point in time.
But if you do not start coming forward
and you do not stop putting your head
down and following orders, we are going
to get to that point, right? Like you
need to start coming out. I think the
entire NSA needs to come out starting
with the director. I think that these
agencies need to start standing up for
something unless they've always wanted
to be the ministry of war, the ministry
of peace and truth or whatever. Like if
that was their goal all along, then all
hope is lost. But, you know, especially
even like our active duty or National
Guard, our service members in uniform in
DC right now, like
I hate using Hollywood and pop culture
as a reference, but like everybody looks
back and admires the conscientious
objectors,
>> admires the people who are willing to
sit in the brig rather than go kill
children abroad or march against their
own people in the streets of BC.
>> Well, reality, I'm twice your age and
exactly and I remember the Vietnam War
and people really did not respect or
treat the conscientious objectors well.
They were treat they were treated and
insulted as cowards and uh made fun of
and ridiculed, but they were heroes.
>> Now they're heroes. But like and that's
the thing too is people need to
understand like people will remember in
time and you have to understand that
history is a process
you know and it's just like also like
just do the right [__] thing. How can
you put on a uniform knowing that you
are being sent to march against the
people of the United States of America?
Like if you wanted to be a bully cop,
you should have gone and been a cop.
You're not. You're a soldier in the
United States military. How dare you
accept those orders?
>> You're here. Um, can you do you um can
we can you talk a little bit well talk
as much as you want about the um about
the uh your prison experience? U I mean
I what I read was really interesting.
>> Yeah. Um county jail was really hard. I
mean it they make it hell for a reason.
Um, yes, the kitty.
Oh, I love the kitty. Um, County Joe was
the lowest point of my life and then the
transport process was even lower. Um,
>> you know, never say rock bottom because
rocks,
>> huh?
>> Did they force you to go through
Oklahoma City?
>> Yes. And I didn't even get the privilege
of going to that transport center. I
went to the overflow Grady County Jail.
>> Oh my god.
>> Yeah. It was a filthy warehouse full of
meth addicts and neo-Nazis.
>> Yeah.
>> Um
>> awful.
>> So, how long So, so you how many how
many years was was it?
>> It was exactly four years to the date
and 15 months of it was in county jails
before I
had the privilege of going to federal
prison. When I showed up at Carwell, I
feel like I made it into Harvard.
>> Yeah, I bet.
>> The campus was beautiful. Like I called
it a campus. It wasn't a compound. Um I
just remember so many of us had been in
county jails for so long. The housing
unit was just one big room with cells
lining the walls
and then like we had a common bathroom
at the end. And our ability to process
like our sensory capacities had been so
limited by that time by just living in
one room for a year that like there was
so many of us looking around like wow
we're going to get lost in here every
day and it's one room. Um, I mean just I
remember getting lost on the compound
and
just like once I got my MP3 player, once
I was able to run and exercise, you
know, life was petty, life was hard, um,
but I was going to be just fine until co
>> Yeah.
>> So, what happened? So, CO hits late
February 2020.
Um, I remember it really well. Uh we all
do. So um what so you went into
lockdown?
>> Yes. So we were a little bit uh behind
the curve just because they were
actually doing like some common sense
stuff like okay so like we're on a
compound. None of y'all should
spontaneously catch COVID.
>> New people coming in. We're going to
quarantine them for a couple weeks just
to see. But y'all should be fine. um
they started decreasing like the
capacity of like the chapel and indoor
spaces like y'all just can't gather like
more than 30 people
>> and then I had taught my last spin class
on like March 14th
and then on March 15th and 16th there
were all these rumors and we had been in
lockdown by the 17th. um you can't go
outside anymore.
And we thought it would just last a
couple days and then it was a week and
then it was two weeks and
they were like, "Yeah, y'all aren't
going outside." And then it was, "Y'all
are only going outside
as long as it takes to search the unit
for drugs and to sanitize everything."
So, like once a week at an unspecified
time, like a fire drill, we would be
ushered out and then they would go in
and allegedly sanitize and look for
drugs.
>> Oh, for heaven's sake.
>> Um, so it was like it was great if I was
ready for it. Like everybody was like,
"Winner, I think they're coming. I think
they're coming." I'd grab my MP3 player,
put my running shoes on, and go run for
an hour while they did that.
Um,
but because it was so like sporadic and
then they started like, "Okay, you guys
get to go out an hour for exercise once
a week." Um,
things were just like it was just so
bad. And then
they put us on lockdown for George
Floyd.
>> Oh.
>> And that was they just they came in like
five officers deep and said, "Get in
your cells." Like like literally like
screaming at us. They were pointing tear
gas guns at us. And like I said, our
prison was unique. We didn't have
toilets in our cells. We didn't have
doors in our cells. We had a common
bathroom at the end, which means in
order for them to facilitate a lockdown,
they had to have 24-hour manned
positions to take bathroom requests.
>> Yeah. Their their parents must have been
so proud.
>> Yeah. Every single day.
They hated it. you and you know
obviously like there were a lot of male
officers so as women
>> asking to go and it's like I had a
miscarriage in my early 20s I have a lot
of scar tissue in my abdomen you know
what I mean I've got like an hour
bladder on a good day like there's so
many women there that also they had
C-sections they had mult five six seven
children like when it comes to female
bodies in particular when you start
talking about limiting their access to
restroom facilities and to hygiene
facilities. That's a human rights issue,
you know, and that's something that our
federal everything in federal prison is
dictated by what the men's compounds
needs
>> because those are 85% of the inmates
because those are the biggest security
concerns. So, when it comes to the
women's compounds, they're like, "Well,
that's not policy. You don't have to
have access to a toilet every hour."
And we're like, "But we need it." Like
when I'm telling you that women were
going
they were urinating in their trash cans
and threatening to throw it out into the
common area if they weren't allowed to
go to the bathroom.
>> Reasonable
>> um things like that. I mean that's what
we went through for a week and we didn't
know why.
>> Nobody told us why we were being treated
that way.
>> Were a lot of your fellow prisoners uh
black? Is that why they were worried
about George Floyd?
It wasn't it had nothing to do with the
prisons. It was that the the marches for
justice on the streets were so were
ramping up to the point to where the
federal government decided to take the
riot task forces
out of the federal prisons to patrol the
streets. that we went into critically
low
um status across the board in federal
prisons which dictated a federal
lockdown. It had nothing to do with our
conduct or our expected
>> So it's just their paranoia.
>> Yeah. For nothing. And that was when I
started using drugs for the first time
because I couldn't I couldn't handle the
injustice
that
we were the ones being punished because
a cop committed a murder in front of the
world. That was that's when I lost my
mind.
>> These drugs are smuggled in by the
guards, I assume.
>> Nope. They were sent in. So, you uh
spray synthetic um synthetic THC on a
piece of paper, like a letter, and then
you send it in, and then they cut it up
into pieces based on how much they want
to charge for the piece,
>> and you just put it under your tongue,
and you just trip for a while.
>> Oh, sort of like the way acid used to
be.
>> Exactly. It was like that. Um, somebody
gave meth once and I told her like, "Not
only am I not going to pay for this
crap, but um, you're lucky I'm not going
to hit you in the face cuz it was so
bad.
Meth was awful. Don't do it."
>> So, were you addicted by the time you uh
your your term you were released?
>> No. Um, I was just like emotionally
dependent on it.
>> And the scary part was just like when I
learned how to balance the use of it
with continuing to work out
cuz if I can like that was the whole
thing. I was like, I'm not going to use
this until I can work out again. Then
I'm going to work out and then I started
using it occasionally.
And it wasn't like such a severe
addiction. It was just like
then all my f everybody around me
started getting busted for it.
and then I still wanted to buy it. So
that was like the thing. It was like the
I was starting to just not even care
about the risks anymore.
That was probably like the most
concerning part.
>> And so
obviously you're not on it now. What
happened?
>> Um supply and demand like they really
cracked down. It wasn't available
anymore. Um,
I hate like this is so stupid, but my
girlfriend really didn't want me to use
it. And then I found out like I was just
using to piss her off. Like I didn't
need anymore. I was just getting high to
make her mad. Um, luckily this is not a
substance that causes withdrawal or
cravings. It's just literally like I
like how this feels. I'm going to do it.
So those are kind of like some of those
things are a little bit easier habits to
break, but also all the drug dealers got
popped at that point in time. So it just
wasn't available. Like I I got really
lucky.
And you're you're if one of the longest,
if not the long the you had the longest
or one of the longest whistleblower
sentences in US history. Yeah.
>> Yeah. I think for any one count, yes.
I'm not really sure about the Jack
Tosher case. I don't know if he's gonna
beat me or not.
>> Yeah, but he wasn't a whistleblower.
>> No,
>> he wasn't. And he had multiple like he
had like hundreds of documents.
>> Yeah.
>> Right.
>> He was trying to impress his friends.
>> He was a braggard.
>> Yeah.
>> Um
uh Okay. So ultimately, um you did your
four years,
you're you're out. You can't make money
from writing books. You can write books,
but you can't make money from
>> I write books. Yeah, you could write as
many as you want. Uh I mean I won't make
any jokes about how, you know, writing
isn't paying any anyone anymore anyway.
Um but uh so okay, so what's your life
been like since then?
>> Um at this moment in time, I'm coaching
CrossFit. It's just a massive privilege
to get to coach my favorite sport. Um I
would be competing, but I'm on book tour
this fall, so kind of taking the fall
off. I also tore my rotator cuff, so
that's kind of been what I've been
dealing with.
>> And right now, I am in a bachelor's
program for veterinary technology.
>> Good for you.
>> And I'm using my VA benefits for that.
So, I still have some benefits. Um, and
I rescue dogs. So, like right now, we
have eight dogs. Um,
>> wow.
>> I'm busy from, you know, 6:00 a.m. to 10
o'clock at night. I'm If I'm not
podcasting, I'm in school coaching or
chasing dogs.
Great
>> reality. Thank you so much for joining
us here. It's uh honestly uh been really
great.
>> Thank you so much. This was fun.
>> Very best of luck with all of it.
>> Yes, you too.
>> Thanks everyone for watching us here on
Drogram with Ted Roll and John Kuryaku.
We're here Monday through Friday at 5:00
p. p.m. Eastern time. Although uh this
is going to air, we recorded this uh
ahead of time last week. This is gonna
air on Tuesday. Um I think October
maybe maybe it's not quite October.
>> September 30th.
>> September 30th. Right. Yeah. And so this
is gonna air September 30th. Um so it's
not live but so this particular starting
tomorrow will be on at 9:00 am Eastern
time. Please like, follow, and share the
show. Reality winner NSA whistleblower.
Thank you so much for joining us.
>> Thanks guys. and buy the book.
>> Yeah.
>> I am not your enemy.
>> All right. If and I will hit This